<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>CrichMath</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/</link>
    <description>Recent content on CrichMath</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- 0.154.5</generator>
    <language>tr-tr</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 02 Feb 2026 12:00:00 +0300</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Introduction to Advanced Calculus</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/introtoadvcalc/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Feb 2026 12:00:00 +0300</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/introtoadvcalc/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;1-historical-facts&#34;&gt;1. Historical Facts&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a common saying that &lt;span style=&#34;color: red;&#34;&gt;physics is applied mathematics&lt;/span&gt;, chemistry is applied physics, and biology is applied chemistry. In the context of this course, we find ourselves in a position where the close relationship between mathematics and physics becomes particularly apparent. Many of the ideas developed in advanced calculus emphasize how deeply physical reasoning is intertwined with mathematical structure.&lt;br&gt;
 This observation should not be interpreted as a claim that mathematics is superior to physics, or vice versa. Rather, it highlights the mutual dependence between the two disciplines. Mathematics provides a precise language and framework, while physics offers concrete motivation and interpretation. Neither can meaningfully advance without the other.&lt;br&gt;
 This perspective became especially clear when I first began studying advanced calculus. A large portion of its core concepts—particularly those belonging to vector calculus—originate from physical problems. The development of notions such as flux, circulation, and divergence was driven by the need to describe physical phenomena like fluid flow, electromagnetic fields, and conservation laws. Many of the theorems encountered in this subject are not abstract constructions, but formal expressions of physical principles.&lt;br&gt;
 During the eighteenth and nineteenth centuries, mathematicians such as Euler, Lagrange, Gauss, and Green developed the foundations of multivariable calculus while studying mechanics, gravitation, and electromagnetism. Their work revealed that integration over curves, surfaces, and volumes is not merely a technical extension of single-variable calculus, but a necessary language for expressing fundamental laws of nature.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Introduction to Calculus I</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/introtocalc1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Feb 2026 12:00:00 +0300</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/introtocalc1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;1-what-is-calculus&#34;&gt;1. What Is Calculus?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Calculus is a fundamental branch of mathematics that provides a rigorous language for describing change and accumulation. It allows us to analyze how quantities vary continuously and how infinitely small changes combine to produce finite results. At its core, calculus is concerned with understanding processes that evolve smoothly rather than in discrete steps, such as motion, growth, heat flow, or variation in physical systems.&lt;br&gt;
 The field is often divided into two sections called differential calculus and integral calculus. In this section, we will be focusing on differential calculus, which is often called in most universities&amp;rsquo; curricula, Calculus I.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Introduction to Calculus II</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/introtocalc2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Feb 2026 12:00:00 +0300</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/introtocalc2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;1-a-comparison&#34;&gt;1. A Comparison&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The way calculus is divided and presented varies significantly across universities and textbooks. In many curricula, calculus is split into two separate courses, commonly referred to as Calculus I and Calculus II. In such settings, Calculus I typically focuses on limits and differentiation, while Calculus II begins with integration, often introduced through Riemann sums, and continues with techniques of integration and applications.&lt;br&gt;
 At Middle East Technical University (METU), however, this division does not appear explicitly. Instead, the standard sequence consists of &lt;em&gt;Calculus with Analytic Geometry&lt;/em&gt; followed by &lt;em&gt;Multivariable Calculus&lt;/em&gt;. While these titles reflect the geometric and multidimensional aspects of the material, they can be somewhat vague in terms of content. For instance, topics such as infinite sequences and series are also covered within Multivariable Calculus, even though they are not inherently multivariable in nature.&lt;br&gt;
 For the purposes of this course, it is therefore useful to adopt a conceptual separation resembling the traditional Calculus I–Calculus II structure. In this framework, the present course will begin with Riemann sums and the theory of integration. This choice is motivated by two main reasons.&lt;br&gt;
 First, from a historical perspective, the notions of limits and differentiation emerged in the 17th century, largely driven by physical problems related to motion, change, and rates. These ideas were developed by Newton and Leibniz as mathematical tools to formalize physical intuition. Integration, on the other hand, acquired its rigorous foundation much later. The definition of the integral via Riemann sums, which interprets integration as the limit of an infinite sum, belongs to the 19th century and is closely associated with the work of Bernhard Riemann. From this viewpoint, it is natural to treat integration as a distinct conceptual development rather than merely the inverse of differentiation.&lt;br&gt;
 Second, the Fundamental Theorem of Calculus plays a central role in unifying differentiation and integration. It establishes a deep and nontrivial connection between two ideas that are, at first glance, conceptually different. Given its importance and its foundational role in the theory of integration, it is pedagogically reasonable to introduce integration as a new topic in its own right, rather than as a continuation of earlier material.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Strong Induction</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/strong/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 21:28:00 +0300</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/strong/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt; &lt;strong&gt;Theorem.(Strong Induction)&lt;/strong&gt; Let $\phi(n)$ be a property of natural numbers. Suppose that $\phi(1)$ holds and for all $n \in \mathbb{N}$, if $\phi(1)$, $\phi(2)$, $\dots$, $\phi(n)$ hold, then $\phi(n+1)$ holds. Then $\phi(n)$ holds for all $n \in \mathbb{N}$.&lt;br&gt;
 Also, we can express this theorem in a similar way to what we did in the previous note as follows:&lt;br&gt;
 Let $S \subseteq \mathbb{N}$. If&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; 1. $1 \in S$&lt;br&gt;
 2. If $k \in S$, and $\{1,2,3, \dots, k\} \subseteq S$, then $k+1 \in S$&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Foundations of Mathematical Reasoning</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/intro-to-foundations/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 20:59:00 +0300</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/intro-to-foundations/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mathematics is not only a collection of formulas and computations, but also a discipline built upon precise reasoning. Before engaging with advanced mathematical structures, it is essential to understand the logical foundations that govern how mathematical statements are formed, interpreted, and justified. This section is devoted to developing that foundational perspective.&lt;br&gt;
 We begin with the classical roots of logic, tracing the basic principles of reasoning back to Aristotle’s formulation of logical laws. From there, we study propositional logic: logical connectives, compound statements, and truth tables, which provide a concrete and systematic way to analyze the validity of logical expressions. These tools allow us to determine when statements are true, false, or logically equivalent, independent of any particular mathematical context.&lt;br&gt;
 Building on this framework, we turn to methods of proof, which form the backbone of mathematical practice. Direct proofs, proof by contradiction, contrapositive arguments.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mathematical Induction and the Successor Function</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/math/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 20:59:00 +0300</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/math/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In mathematics, most basic operations feel intuitive. Consider multiplication or summation. We, without any mathematical thinking, only apply the algorithms that will give us the answer. However, every mathematical algorithm, actually, originate from some theorems.&lt;br&gt;
 In this part, before mathematical induction, it is important to know the Successor Function and its applications, and furthermore, how it is related to induction.&lt;br&gt;
 Let there be a function whose domain and codomain is $\mathbb{N}$ with the property that every natural number has the image of the successor natural number under this function.&lt;br&gt;
 &lt;strong&gt;Definition.&lt;/strong&gt; The successor function is a mathematical function that takes a natural number and returns the next natural number in the sequence. The successor function is denoted by $S$.&lt;br&gt;
 
In other words, the successor function is given by $S : \mathbb{N} \to \mathbb{N}$ such that $S(n)=n+1$ for all $n \in \mathbb{N}$.&lt;br&gt;
 
&lt;strong&gt;Definition.&lt;/strong&gt; An axiom is a statement that is assumed to be true without proof and is used as a starting point to derive other statements (theorems) using logical reasoning, i.e., a basic assumption in a formal system from which all other results are deduced.&lt;br&gt;
 
&lt;span style=&#34;color: blue&#34;&gt;Pieno Axioms:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Well Ordering Principle</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/well-ordering/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 19:59:00 +0300</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/well-ordering/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt; &lt;strong&gt;Well Ordering Principle:&lt;/strong&gt; Every nonempty subset of $\mathbb{N}$ has a least element, i.e., there exists $a \in S$ such that $x \geq a$ for all $x \in S$.&lt;br&gt;
 This principle may seem a little obvious. The conditions, however, are considerable. Notice that, firstly, we need a nonempty set. The reason is trivial to comprehend, as the empty set has no elements and therefore it cannot have a least element. Furthermore, the set must be a subset of $\mathbb{N}$.&lt;br&gt;
 We can consider some sets and determine whether they satisfy the Well Ordering Principle, i.e., they are well ordered.
&lt;br&gt;
 &lt;span style=&#34;color: blue&#34;&gt;Example:&lt;/span&gt; Consider the set&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Introduction to Elementary Number Theory</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/intro-number-theory/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 18:15:00 +0300</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/intro-number-theory/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt; Elementary number theory is the branch of mathematics concerned with the study of the integers and their fundamental properties.&lt;br&gt;
 Unlike many areas of mathematics that rely heavily on continuous structures, number theory focuses on discrete objects and exact relationships. Its questions are often simple to state, yet surprisingly deep, and many have shaped the development of modern mathematics.&lt;br&gt;
 At its core, number theory seeks to understand the structure of the integers: how numbers divide one another, how primes are distributed, and how arithmetic behaves under various constraints.&lt;br&gt;
 Despite its elementary appearance, number theory plays a central role in areas ranging from algebra and analysis to cryptography and computer science.&lt;br&gt;
 It is highly recommended for students who major in computer engineering or physics to study elementary number theory, as it helps in understanding the patterns and behaviors.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Homogeneous Differential Equations</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/homogenus-diff/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 12:30:00 +0300</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/homogenus-diff/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Some first order ordinary differential equations are not separable, but we can convert them into separable equations after applying simple substitution. Such equations are called &lt;span style=&#34;color: red&#34;&gt;homogeneous equations&lt;/span&gt;. In this section, we will discuss how to apply this substitution and solve such equations.&lt;br&gt; &lt;strong&gt;Definition.&lt;/strong&gt; A first order ordinary differential equation is called &lt;span style=&#34;color: red&#34;&gt;homogeneous&lt;/span&gt; if it can be expressed in the form&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$ \frac{dy}{dx}=f\left(\frac{y}{x}\right) $$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;for some function $f$. The given expression may seem a little devious, but an equivalent and often more practical way to verify that a function is homogeneous is through its scaling behavior.&lt;br&gt;  Let&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Initial Value Problems</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/initial-value/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 12:30:00 +0300</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/initial-value/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt; &lt;strong&gt;Definition.&lt;/strong&gt; First-order differential equations are differential equations that only involve the first order derivatives of a specific variable with respect to another variable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color: orange&#34;&gt;Examples:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$
\frac{dy}{dx}=2x, \qquad
y&amp;rsquo;= \arctan(x) + e^x, \qquad
(2xe^x)\left(\frac{dy}{dx}\right)=\sin(\arctan(x))
$$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;strong&gt;Definition.&lt;/strong&gt; Degrees of freedom refers to the number of independent data that can successfully estimate a parameter.&lt;br&gt;
 This may feel a little vague. But think about this; you have computed the result of an indefinite integral, say&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Newton&#39;s Law of Cooling</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/newton/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 03:00:00 +0300</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/newton/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Newton&amp;rsquo;s Law of Cooling is a fundamental principle in heat transfer. It states that the rate at which a body loses heat is directly proportional to the difference between its temperature and that of its surrounding environment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As this definition suggests, the study of Newton&amp;rsquo;s Law of Cooling inherently involves differential equations. In fact, the applications of differential equations are extremely broad, since many natural phenomena can be described and analyzed in terms of rates of change.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Separable Equations</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/separable-equations/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 23:59:00 +0300</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/separable-equations/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt; Now, we consider some specific methods to solve differential equations. The aim is mostly to consider $y$ as a variable dependent on $x$ and solve the equation for $y$. It is, however, common to leave the expressions in implicit forms. One of the most elementary types of differential equations is separable equations.&lt;br&gt;
 A first-order differential equation is said to be separable if it can be written in a form where all terms involving the dependent variable $y$ and its differential $dy$ appear on one side of the equation, while all terms involving the independent variable $x$ and its differential $dx$ appear on the other side.&lt;br&gt;
It looks like the following:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Friendly Introduction to Differential Equations</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/introtodiff/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/introtodiff/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The key to jump into differential equations is to first understand the meaning of differentials in the first place. Consider $ dx $ or $ dy $, do they have a considerable meaning alone? The answer to this question is both yes and no, and this is actually one of some concepts which mathematicians and engineers, or applied mathematicians prefer dealing in different ways.
In prereqruisite calculus, the reader studied differentiation and is familiar with the expression $\frac{dy}{dx}$. This mathematical expression tells us how fast the dependent variable $y$ changes.&lt;br&gt;
 In the study of differential equations, the symbols $dx$ and $dy$ will be treated as if they were fractions rather than operators, and we will assume that basic algebraic manipulations apply to these expressions.&lt;br&gt;
 It should be understood, however, that each such manipulation is ultimately justified by fundamental results of calculus, such as the chain rule or the manipulations of the limit definition of derivatives. Here, for simplicity, these justifications will not be proved, and will rely instead on intuitive reasoning. From now on, under these circumstances, we call $dx$, where $x$ is the expression of any variable, a differential.&lt;br&gt;
 Now, let&amp;rsquo;s talk about the equations that involve differentials, which are evidently called differential equations. Consider $$\frac{dy}{dx}=2$$
This is a familiar expression. We infer, here, letting $y$ be the dependent variable, that an infinitesimal change in $x$, say $dx$, results in a change of $2dx$ in $y$. But also, we can infer that the derivative of such $y$ is equal to 2 in the corresponding domain, everywhere. Considering these, we can furthermore evolve our understanding and say $y$ is a function of $x$ and it is of the form $y(x)= 2x + C $, where C is a constant. Apparently, C can take any value, so long as it is a arbitrary constant, since the derivative of C with respect to $x$ is identically zero.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>About</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Feb 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/about/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I am Selim Kaan Özsoy from Turkey. I have been studying at Middle East Technical University (METU) since 2023. After completing two years as a Mechanical Engineering major, I started a double major in Mathematics in 2025, and I plan to begin a minor in Physics in the Spring of 2026.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have been interested in teaching and writing since high school. When I began studying mathematics and became familiar with mathematical writing, I realized how naturally clear exposition and scientific thinking come together in this field. As I explored the structure and style of mathematical texts, I gradually developed a strong interest in writing my own lecture notes.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
