<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Elementary Number Theory on CrichMath</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/categories/elementary-number-theory/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Elementary Number Theory on CrichMath</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- 0.154.5</generator>
    <language>tr-tr</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 21:28:00 +0300</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/categories/elementary-number-theory/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Strong Induction</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/strong/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 21:28:00 +0300</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/strong/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt; &lt;strong&gt;Theorem.(Strong Induction)&lt;/strong&gt; Let $\phi(n)$ be a property of natural numbers. Suppose that $\phi(1)$ holds and for all $n \in \mathbb{N}$, if $\phi(1)$, $\phi(2)$, $\dots$, $\phi(n)$ hold, then $\phi(n+1)$ holds. Then $\phi(n)$ holds for all $n \in \mathbb{N}$.&lt;br&gt;
 Also, we can express this theorem in a similar way to what we did in the previous note as follows:&lt;br&gt;
 Let $S \subseteq \mathbb{N}$. If&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; 1. $1 \in S$&lt;br&gt;
 2. If $k \in S$, and $\{1,2,3, \dots, k\} \subseteq S$, then $k+1 \in S$&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mathematical Induction and the Successor Function</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/math/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 20:59:00 +0300</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/math/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In mathematics, most basic operations feel intuitive. Consider multiplication or summation. We, without any mathematical thinking, only apply the algorithms that will give us the answer. However, every mathematical algorithm, actually, originate from some theorems.&lt;br&gt;
 In this part, before mathematical induction, it is important to know the Successor Function and its applications, and furthermore, how it is related to induction.&lt;br&gt;
 Let there be a function whose domain and codomain is $\mathbb{N}$ with the property that every natural number has the image of the successor natural number under this function.&lt;br&gt;
 &lt;strong&gt;Definition.&lt;/strong&gt; The successor function is a mathematical function that takes a natural number and returns the next natural number in the sequence. The successor function is denoted by $S$.&lt;br&gt;
 
In other words, the successor function is given by $S : \mathbb{N} \to \mathbb{N}$ such that $S(n)=n+1$ for all $n \in \mathbb{N}$.&lt;br&gt;
 
&lt;strong&gt;Definition.&lt;/strong&gt; An axiom is a statement that is assumed to be true without proof and is used as a starting point to derive other statements (theorems) using logical reasoning, i.e., a basic assumption in a formal system from which all other results are deduced.&lt;br&gt;
 
&lt;span style=&#34;color: blue&#34;&gt;Pieno Axioms:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Well Ordering Principle</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/well-ordering/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 19:59:00 +0300</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/well-ordering/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt; &lt;strong&gt;Well Ordering Principle:&lt;/strong&gt; Every nonempty subset of $\mathbb{N}$ has a least element, i.e., there exists $a \in S$ such that $x \geq a$ for all $x \in S$.&lt;br&gt;
 This principle may seem a little obvious. The conditions, however, are considerable. Notice that, firstly, we need a nonempty set. The reason is trivial to comprehend, as the empty set has no elements and therefore it cannot have a least element. Furthermore, the set must be a subset of $\mathbb{N}$.&lt;br&gt;
 We can consider some sets and determine whether they satisfy the Well Ordering Principle, i.e., they are well ordered.
&lt;br&gt;
 &lt;span style=&#34;color: blue&#34;&gt;Example:&lt;/span&gt; Consider the set&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Introduction to Elementary Number Theory</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/intro-number-theory/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 18:15:00 +0300</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/intro-number-theory/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt; Elementary number theory is the branch of mathematics concerned with the study of the integers and their fundamental properties.&lt;br&gt;
 Unlike many areas of mathematics that rely heavily on continuous structures, number theory focuses on discrete objects and exact relationships. Its questions are often simple to state, yet surprisingly deep, and many have shaped the development of modern mathematics.&lt;br&gt;
 At its core, number theory seeks to understand the structure of the integers: how numbers divide one another, how primes are distributed, and how arithmetic behaves under various constraints.&lt;br&gt;
 Despite its elementary appearance, number theory plays a central role in areas ranging from algebra and analysis to cryptography and computer science.&lt;br&gt;
 It is highly recommended for students who major in computer engineering or physics to study elementary number theory, as it helps in understanding the patterns and behaviors.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
