<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Foundations of Mathematical Reasoning on CrichMath</title>
    <link>//localhost:1313/categories/foundations-of-mathematical-reasoning/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Foundations of Mathematical Reasoning on CrichMath</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- 0.154.5</generator>
    <language>tr-tr</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 20:59:00 +0300</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="//localhost:1313/categories/foundations-of-mathematical-reasoning/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Foundations of Mathematical Reasoning</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/posts/intro-to-foundations/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 20:59:00 +0300</pubDate>
      <guid>//localhost:1313/posts/intro-to-foundations/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mathematics is not only a collection of formulas and computations, but also a discipline built upon precise reasoning. Before engaging with advanced mathematical structures, it is essential to understand the logical foundations that govern how mathematical statements are formed, interpreted, and justified. This section is devoted to developing that foundational perspective.&lt;br&gt;
 We begin with the classical roots of logic, tracing the basic principles of reasoning back to Aristotle’s formulation of logical laws. From there, we study propositional logic: logical connectives, compound statements, and truth tables, which provide a concrete and systematic way to analyze the validity of logical expressions. These tools allow us to determine when statements are true, false, or logically equivalent, independent of any particular mathematical context.&lt;br&gt;
 Building on this framework, we turn to methods of proof, which form the backbone of mathematical practice. Direct proofs, proof by contradiction, contrapositive arguments.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
